It was a way for people
to authentically connect to one another
and have a community
and get to know people
based on their values
without necessarily being salesy.
Stephanie Andrews, thank you so much
for joining me on 20 Minute Leaders.
How are you?
I'm great. How are you?
I'm doing fine.
Thank you so much for joining me.
Thank you for being generous
with your time.
I can't wait to talk to you about
your journey, about co-founding a startup
with your two best friends.
And more importantly, about
the world of podcasting.
So, I've had the privilege
of being a podcaster for,
I guess, about almost 8 months now.
And I've seen the ups and downs of it.
But I'm excited to learn about
the industry from you.
So, Stephanie, before we get started,
can you tell me
a little bit about yourself
and what you're doing at Quill today?
Yeah, absolutely.
Hi, I'm Steph to everyone listening.
And I am currently
Quill's Head of Production.
Prior to that,
I was the co-founder and CEO
of a startup called Origins Media Haus,
which was a boutique podcast
and video agency in Toronto.
And it definitely wasn't
a linear path to get there.
We pivoted multiple times.
We actually started
the company as a online magazine back
when I was in my first year of university.
And over three to four years we pivoted,
tried to understand
the content creation world,
and eventually landed on podcasting
as a way for brands
to connect really interestingly
with their consumers.
Because it was a way for people
to authentically connect to one another
and have a community
and get to know people
based on their values
without necessarily being salesy.
So, that's really what we stood for
as a company,
as we wanted to make sure
that brands were connecting
with their consumers in a way
that was authentic and it was real.
And it wasn't just like a sales pitch
or buy this or buy this.
We wanted people
to make informed decisions.
And so, that was really kind
of our bread and butter
and where we started
and how we landed
on the podcasting realm.
And yeah, so then we ended up getting a part.
So, before we move on to that other part,
I have to understand a little bit better
the pain point
that you're trying to solve.
So, you're mentioning that
you're looking at podcasting
as a tool for brands
to engage with their users
in a more authentic way,
less salesy way.
Can you paint me a picture of what
that looks like today
or what it looked like
a few years ago
when you were just getting started?
Because I do know that podcasting
is that at peak. Right?
We're seeing more and more podcasts.
But what is it about podcasting
that is so engaging and non-salesy?
Yeah.
So, what's really interesting
about podcasting in my opinion is
it's kind of a two fold.
So, one is your connection
with the host of the show.
And then the second is really
the convenience of the medium itself
as being the audio.
So, one, being able
to connect to a host.
When you're able to listen
to someone for 40 minutes,
a really good host should sound like
you're talking to a good friend.
It should sound like
you're just on the phone.
You don't have to say anything
and you're comfortable.
And what that does is
it builds a really interesting
parasocial relationship where you're
the host is able to essentially
talk to you and talk to your values
and you're able to relate to them
and feel like you know them,
but you've never actually met them.
And what that does is,
as a friend, let's say,
if this host is maybe the CEO
of a company then
and you connect with their values,
then you're going to be more likely
to like that company
and you're going to be more likely
to probably buy from that brand.
Let's say it's a consumer brand.
Right?
And so, for example,
there's been some really interesting
shows that have used this.
So, Breadwinners is an example
from Harvest Bread
where what they did
was they created a show
all about women empowerment
and women breadwinners.
And what that did is
it showed that this bread brand
had like values and it had,
it wanted to empower women.
And so women listening are like,
okay, well, if I'm going
to buy bread brands
and I believe in these values,
I'm going to buy Harvest right?
So, that's kind
of the interesting part of it,
podcasting from a connection standpoint.
And then in the medium,
what's interesting is if you look
at video, if you look at blogs,
the correlation to those two mediums
is you have to be staring at a screen.
And especially today,
I think when we look at covid
and the pandemic,
what are we doing all day every day
is just staring at screen.
It's like you stare at the middle screen
and then you go off work
and then you stare at the big screen
and then you stare
at your small screen
when you're talking to someone
and you just can't get away from it.
So, podcasting offers a really nice,
convenient medium where
you can literally listen to it anywhere.
You can listen to it in your car
while you're driving,
you can listen to it
while taking a shower,
while you're cooking,
whatever you want.
And video and blogs
just can't offer that.
And especially today
when we look at how fast everything
is rapidly evolving,
humans are trying to constantly keep up
and humans are trying to constantly
consume information.
And so, podcasting offers
a convenient way
to be consistently consuming
without necessarily having
to put energy into consuming.
So, that makes all sense.
So, I'm completely sold on this idea
that podcasting is important,
it's something relevant,
it's extremely relevant for brands.
I feel a little bit silly that
we're doing this over a video then.
But good thing that we're also taking
the audio for Spotify
and Apple podcasts, at least that.
I'll give you a pass.
Thank you.
Give me a little bit
of a higher understanding as to
the market of podcasting.
How many are there like,
how many people podcast generally
or listeners?
I really don't know.
Yeah.
So, podcasting is actually
a really interesting medium
from an audience standpoint because
it's all made up
of mostly affluent millennials.
And obviously that's expanded a bit
since podcasting has kind of
increased over the years.
But the base of it is really
that niche audience.
And people are highly educated as well.
And so, if you're looking
for brands, it's kind of
this beautiful medium because
it's people who generally have
a higher income,
who are wanting
to connect with values,
who have that kind of higher,
they're looking for basically brands
to connect to.
They're looking for that information
and they're looking for brands
that are conscious, I would say.
So that's interesting
from an audience standpoint.
In terms of how big the market is,
there's over a million podcasts.
But what people don't realize,
is that there's a ton of podcasts out there
that aren't active.
A million podcast?
Yeah.
We surpass a million this year as well.
But what people don't realize
is that sounds like a lot.
But it's really not, because if you look at
how many videos there are,
if you look at how many blogs there are,
there's so many more.
And then on top of that,
if you look at the podcasting industry
out of that million,
there's so many that are inactive.
So, when you're actually starting a podcast,
if you're going to actually
do it properly,
you're going to be consistent.
You're going to be putting out episodes.
You're going
to look at it like a marathon,
not a sprint.
You're going to consistently
put out episodes.
Your ability to build an audience
is going to be a lot greater
than it would in my opinion,
than any other medium
out there right now.
Wow.
Okay, so where we seeing this going?
So, do we see
a continuous linear growth,
exponential growth?
Are more brands understanding this?
What's happening to the market?
Yeah.
So in terms of the market right now,
we're seeing a lot
of brands invest pretty heavily
into podcasting ads.
And I think people
are starting to kind of open their eyes.
Specifically in the US,
you'll see a lot of brands that
are having,
a lot of brands that have
their own podcasts already.
Canada, I think is a little bit behind.
But that's usual.
Not surprising there.
And you're from Canada, right?
But it's.
Oh yeah.
Yeah. I'm from Toronto.
So, I'm very used to
the conservative nature of Canadians.
But yeah.
So, I would say that
the media industry honestly is just much
it's just more advanced down south.
So, yeah, we're starting to see
a lot of brands kind
of pour more dollars into it.
And I personally think that
in the next couple of years
we're going to start seeing
the same trend as videos, like eventually
I think there's going to be people
whose job titles are podcast marketers.
And I think it's going to be
a mainstream media that
you just have to have as a brand
and as part of your playbook.
That makes a lot of sense.
So, tell me a little bit about
your entrepreneurial journey
with creating a company
with two of your best friends.
Yeah, sure.
So, when we started the company,
I was literally 17 years old.
And I remember,
I walked into my first year
of university business class.
And the first thing that the prof said
was that 95% of startups fail.
And so, me being a small
17 year old human
who wanted to start her company so bad,
I was like, great, that's fabulous.
And so, I basically being someone
who in high school,
I was like a straight-A student.
I was very perfectionists
and I never failed at anything.
And so I was like, okay,
so, how do I not fail at this?
I'm going to go and interview the 5%
of entrepreneurs that are successful
and figure out how they did it.
And so, long story short,
we ended up creating an online magazine
where we interviewed over
100 entrepreneurs, Britt and Ali,
my two co-founders ended up coming
into the folds a few months after
I kind of conceptualized it.
And we were all
in our first year university
at that point.
And basically we started interviewing,
interviewing, interviewing.
And started to build it up.
Britt was an amazing
at technical video production, recording,
of anything web related.
She was just really good
at figuring things out.
I tended to be more on the marketing
and business development side,
getting into interviews.
And Ali was always really good
at kind of tying those two worlds together
in terms of content creation and brand,
which neither Britt and I really have
much of an eye for, I would say.
So, it kind of worked out really well
and we realized
that we really loved working
with each other.
Although that came up
with its ups and downs,
sometimes being friends.
Sometimes it's a little hard
to be transparent
when you're giving constructive feedback
and that kind of stuff.
And it was something,
a challenge that we had to work around.
But we ended up pivoting several times
to try and make the magazine work.
So, whether that was
a website we design
or whether it was pivoting
the type of content.
So, Interviewing entrepreneurs
about their journey.
Let's talk about their failures.
And we tried to pivot
and pivot and pivot
and get an audience around it.
And what we realized was
just it wasn't working.
And this was two years in,
yeah, that's two and a half years in.
We were incubated,
a accelerator called the Trans Media Zone
at Ryerson University in Toronto.
And that was the point where
they started to kind of sit us down
and be like, all right,
like you guys need
to figure out what you're doing.
This is clearly isn't working.
Like your audience isn't growing
so, what can you do.
And at that point,
we had luckily started experimenting
with podcasting actually, as a way
to interview entrepreneurs,
and as an extension
of this online magazine thing
that we were trying to make.
And at the time,
I was also working full time,
as well as also being in school, too.
And while I was at my full time job,
I was working in business development
at a tech startup.
And what I was doing was
I would go find conferences
and then I would basically try
and find executives
and essentially hunt them down
at conferences to try
and sell them our software at the booth.
And that was pretty much my main role.
And I just felt it was
really inauthentic.
It was awful.
It was so terrible.
And I remember always just feeling like
there was something
that I could be doing
and that would create
a better connection with someone.
And that's actually where the idea
for branded podcasts really sparked.
Because I was like,
what if you could put an executive
and a startup in the same room together
and they could talk about
something related to it
and that would actually build
a genuine connection.
And so, we ended up starting
a show called The Tech Haus,
which was our first ever original podcast
as Origins Media House,
which is the company
that we eventually evolved into.
And that's exactly what it was.
We put Fortune 500 execs with startups
talk about the future of technology
and that show went okay.
It didn't do great,
It didn't do amazing, but still running.
So, that's good.
And while we were doing that,
we realized, oh, well, maybe
what's actually going
to make the money here is
if we got brands to pay us
to make their shows for us.
And so we pivoted again
and then eventually found our niche.
And the product market fit
was really like getting brands
to pay us to do full service production.
And that's where we found
our bread and butter.
After four long years.
That's a pretty fascinating thing.
Thank you for sharing that.
And I can't imagine how difficult
it must be to be co-founding a startup
with two of your best friends.
I love the pivoting.
I love the insights along the way.
It's really just
the pure entrepreneurial journey.
So thank you very, very much
for sharing that.
What do you do today
as head of production at Quill?
Yeah, so head of production is
an interesting role.
I would say it was a little odd
to transition from being a CEO into
this role today.
But now that it's been a few months,
I actually I've really enjoyed it.
It's great.
It's a lot less stress
and I'm really lucky to have
an incredible team that I work with.
But basically my role
as head of production
is basically to make sure
that a show goes
from initial idea and concept,
mapping that out,
making sure that there is going to be
an audience for it
as best as I can,
and making sure that
we're going to hit the goals
with the concept that we have,
building up the structure
and then basically taking that
and rolling it out
to make sure that
we execute it properly,
making sure that everything
gets booked in,
making sure that
the recordings go smoothly,
making sure that the content is
as good as it can be
in the post-production
and editing process.
And then from there,
working on distribution,
making sure it goes smoothly
onto all the platforms,
and then also working
on the second half of the challenge
when you're creating a podcast,
which is audience growth.
So, working there
and figuring out, okay,
how do we look at the show
not necessarily as just a podcast,
an extension of a brand,
but how do we look at a podcast
as a brand in and of itself.
And so then
how do we grow an audience
and a community around that's going
to rally around this idea
which then will feed back
into your brand.
I think a lot of people kind
of look at it opposite to that.
And at this point,
I think we just start looking
at podcasts and shows as
brands in and of themselves.
That's really interesting.
I didn't think of podcasts
in such a way until now.
But it makes perfect sense
from the similar experience
that I've been having
with this and it's been a lot of fun.
So, I know quite a few people
who are running podcasts.
Now that we're talking
about how big the market is getting.
I am reflecting back
and I'm realizing
that I have a lot of friends
that are starting podcast,
that have already been running podcasts.
What are some high level
or low level pointers
that we can provide to some of
to myself and some of my friends
on how to create a successful podcast?
And when I say successful,
I mean engaging with
the right audience
and having speaking to them
and having them really interact
with the content.
Oh, yes. I love this question.
So, there's a couple of different ways.
And I always say
it's almost like a road map
that you should follow.
And I actually pretty much stole this
from building a business.
But basically what you need to do,
it's the first thing when you're starting
a podcast is think about
what are you trying
to actually achieve.
I think a lot of people,
when they're starting a show,
they're like, oh yeah.
I'm just going to start a show
and it'll be a fun side hustle.
And it's like, okay, cool.
But like, what's the point?
At the end of the day,
when things are really hard
and you're going to have
to edit for hours to make sure
that the show gets out on time,
what's going to make you go back to it
and say, yes, this is worth it.
Right?
Because if you don't have that thing
that is telling you that your show
is worth doing
and the time that you're putting into it
is worth doing,
then your show is going to flop.
Because you're going to do maybe
five to 10 episodes.
You're going to be like,
this is a lot of work.
And that's going to be that.
Unless you go and hire someone,
which most indie podcasters won't,
because this is generally
can be very expensive to hire someone
unless you're just doing parts
of the process, maybe like
you're outsourcing another here.
But anyways, so, first things first.
Start with the goal.
Next, what you want to do
is you want to think about your ILP
or your Ideal Listener Profile.
And so full disclosure,
I fully stole this
from ideal customer profile.
But what you want to do is map out
who exactly your target listener is.
So, who are they,
what age are they,
what gender are they,
what are their hobbies,
what are their interests,
why do they want to listen
to this podcast,
what are their motivators in life, like,
what do they need to hear from you.
Essentially, what are their
behaviors every day,
like what are their hobbies.
I want to know all of that.
Because then when you're talking
and shaping the content
and the structure,
you're going to know what's going
to engage them better because
you're thinking of it from
a listeners first standpoint.
And a lot of podcasters
that I think also start
from this place of
I'm going to start with me
and I'm going to start
with my content
and what I want,
instead of thinking about,
well, what do the listeners want,
what does the audience want.
Right?
And just like a company,
if you start a company
and you say,
I want to build a product
because I like it
and you're not considering
what your customers want,
it's not going to be very successful.
Right?
And so, it's the same thing
with podcasting.
You have to look at it
from a listener standpoint.
Your listeners are your customers
at the end of the day.
And then from there,
once you have kind of like
your ideal listener profile mapped out,
can be like a two pager, it's fine.
One pager even.
Then, what I like to do
and what we do at Quill
is we do a positioning
or a competitive matrix.
So, take a look at
the type of show that
you're thinking you're going to create. Right?
By this point,
you kind of probably thinking
you have a concept,
you know what category it's going to be.
Let's say
it's an entrepreneurship podcast
like this one.
And look at the category.
So the entrepreneurship category
on Apple will be like, okay,
what are the top podcasts in my category.
Map it out,
maybe do like six or seven.
However many you want.
And then take a look
and think about them
in terms of show duration,
in terms of post engagement,
think about their structure
and rip them apart and be like, okay,
what did I do really, really well
and what did I not do really well.
What did I not engage with
and then map it all out
and find the patterns.
So, find the patterns of what
they're all not doing well
or what listeners aren't
necessarily getting from the top shows
in your category
and then provide that value.
So, that's basically my philosophy
on how to create a successful show,
because once you have all
of those pieces together,
you can map out a structure
that's going to be effective
and engaging for your listeners.
And also, just another side note,
a lot of people also that
I've met that are doing podcasts,
generally, people think of it as a sprint
and not a marathon.
And podcasting,
when you put out your first episode,
it's okay to have fifty listeners.
You're not going
to have thousands and thousands
of people listening
to you right off the bat.
That's totally fine because
listeners accumulate over time.
The whole idea of podcast
is you need to be consistent
and constantly putting episode out,
episode out, episodes out.
Right?
And then your audience
will build over time
as people discover you,
as you get more guys,
as you get more exposure.
And so just because
you put out 10 episodes
and maybe you only have like
3,000 listeners on the entire show.
That's actually not necessarily
a bad thing,
just keep going and keep going,
and then eventually
you'll do 20 and then maybe you'll have
6,000 or even 10,000 by then.
And then that's metrics
that you can get behind
and you can present to sponsors,
if that's what you're looking for.
So, yeah, that's basically
my general advice for podcasting.
I think
I'm definitely going to take that to heart.
And obviously,
even once you have the whole structure
in the envelope around it,
you still do the hard work
of actually producing quality content
and having fun.
And I think that
when I thought about going into
this project myself,
I never thought of it as quitting
a podcast or quitting a show.
I thought of it,
how can I engage
with really interesting  people
in all sorts of industries
and get their nuggets
and insights from their life.
Things that I am truly interested in,
having a truly fascinating
conversation for me.
And, you know, by association,
a lot of my friends
that are also like minded with me,
will also be interested.
But Steph, I really want
to thank you for being
so generous with your time.
It's been really, really wonderful
and very insightful.
So thank you.
And before we leave,
I have to ask you for three words
that you would use to describe yourself.
Oh, Lord, I have to think about it.
Even though I've had like a full half
and an hour to think about it
because you told me
that you would ask this question.
All right.
So, I'd say the first word.
Oh, Okay.
I'd say the first word is probably,
ambitious, I guess.
The second word I would say
is connected.
I generally like not connected
in the sense of being well connected.
But I would say my biggest
curiosity in life is how people connect
to one another
and how we connect
to the world around us.
So, I'd say that's a big one for me.
And the third one,
I would say quirky, I guess.
I don't know.
I love that.
People have told me that a lot.
So there you go.
That's perfect.
Steph, thank you very much.
Stay safe and stay healthy.
Thank you.
Yes, you too. Thank you.