Wonderful. Okay.
Fatima Zaidi, thank you so much
for being on my show.
How are you?
I'm doing well.
Thank you for having me.
Of course.
Where are you calling from right now?
I am currently based out of Toronto.
As soon as the pandemic happened,
I came back home.
Because, well, we have free health care.
Very well info now.
And some good leadership behind us.
So, yeah, we're in good shape down here.
Wonderful.
But you actually have a long history
with Toronto, with the various startups
that you've worked with, right?
So, have you been on the line between
the United States and Toronto often?
I would say I was born and raised
in the Middle East
and I moved to North America
when I was just turning 17.
And I definitely have spent
a large part of my career in Canada.
And then this last company
that I've started,
which is called Quill,
it's a one stop shop marketplace
for podcasters.
So, if you're an indie podcaster,
or a company looking to start a show
or even outsource elements of your show,
we work with companies
on indie podcasters
to scale through their podcasts.
So, right after this,
you're going to help me learn
how to scale my own podcasts, obviously.
I was going to make a joke
right at the beginning being like,
"Oh, you're recording on a zoom."
"I don't want to be too critical here."
But no, it's great.
I love that you're in university
and I love that you're starting a podcast.
You're definitely ahead of the hype curve.
But just due to the nature
of this business,
we are more US focused.
So, I would say most of the brands
that we're working with
and we own a conference out in LA.
So, I would say that I have been spending
the majority of my time
the last couple of years
based out of different parts of the US.
Whether it be Chicago or LA
where our event is.
But as soon as the pandemic happened,
I was on the first flight home.
And I'm staying right here
until the foreseeable future.
I love it. I love it. Okay.
Definitely. Definitely.
So, what I was saying is that
I'd love for you to take me
a little bit about back to your journey.
You're both named, No, we're fine.
You were both named the top 30 marketers
by marketing magazine.
You share the stage with Richard Branson
and places like the Web Summit
and other conferences
as part of the National Speakers Bureau.
So, talk to me a little bit
about this dynamic.
You were both in marketing.
VP business development
in various startups.
One of them appeared on the Dragon's Den.
The Canada version of Shark Tank.
So, who are you Fatima?
And what drives you
to these different endeavors?
Yeah, it's a great question.
I would say first and foremost,
I'm definitely a sales person.
So, when I moved to Canada,
I didn't really have a dime to my name.
But I knew that I wanted to build a life
for myself here.
It was one of the few countries
in the world that I thought
could provide you opportunities
based on merit and hard work,
regardless of the color of your skin
and your gender.
And so, I'm really glad
that I made the decision to move.
I worked corporate gigs, while at first
I had to put myself to university.
So, I did part time at jobs.
Got three jobs through school.
And eventually graduated debt free
and joined the corporate world.
And I've always been in sales.
And so, the corporate world taught me
a lot of the structured processes
behind sales.
But then, eventually,
I moved into the entrepreneurship
and startup space
where I would help companies scale.
And I would say
I'm definitely good at marketing
because I've worked with
tech marketing agencies
to scale their companies.
But I'm definitely not a marketing expert.
I would call myself 100% a sales person.
And that is why I started my own company,
because I wanted to work
on my own bottom line and pipeline
rather than somebody else's.
So, give me a few of the insights
that you've learned about sales
over these years.
What are some of the
key foundational things
that excite you about this industry
that as a young entrepreneur,
I might not even be aware of?
Well, being in sales
is an emotional rollercoaster.
Some days you're,
very similar to entry into the startup
and entrepreneurship world
where some days you feel like
you're on the top of the world
and some days it's rock bottom.
And I think that good sales people
realized that they shouldn't be taking
these rejections personally.
It takes a lot more work
getting your ducks in a row
than simply managing and to line up
and say,
I'm hiring for my sales team.
I'm always looking for people
who are extremely resilient.
People who don't feel rejection
and people who have the ability
to keep putting themselves.
Being a salesperson has really trained me
to becoming a really great entrepreneur.
And essentially it's the same DNA
that's required.
Right. So, now talk to me a little bit
about this latest experience with Quill.
What are you trying to do
and how are you bringing
those sales insights
into this new endeavor?
So, I was running an agency
for a few years
where we used to do marketing
for a lot of corporate clients.
And my job was primarily
bringing in the revenue.
And I eventually saw a gap in the market
where I started seeing a lot of brands
were moving into the podcasting space.
And so, I decided
to productize our services.
I sold the agency and launched Quill,
which is the world's
first marketplace for podcasters.
We still have an agency umbrella
to the business because a lot of those
corporate companies came back and said,
"Well, it's great that you have
a marketplace and a product.
But what we also need
is a full service team around us."
So, we have both.
We have the scalable
online technology platform
similar to Fiverr and UpWork
for podcasting.
And then we also have
our in-house service team
where we do podcasts for big brands
along with our conference.
And so, that's really the reason
that I impetus of why I decided to launch.
And we've been working on this company
for almost a year now
and we launched right before the pandemic.
So, that was
an interesting experience as well.
Launching a company
right through the pandemic
and then actually scaling
during the pandemic
was a very interesting experience.
So, talk to me a little bit
about this world of podcasting.
And I've just discovered this
in the recent months since covid started.
Because I used to go and meet
a lot of people that I speak with.
I used to meet them for coffee
or for walks or go to their offices.
All of a sudden covid hits.
And I'm like, okay,
now I have to do Zoom.
Well, actually, when I'm visiting them
in the office,
it's really weird to just bring
a video and then station
and then shoot.
But if we're on Zoom
hitting record, we almost forget
that we're recording this right now.
We're actually recording
an episode right now.
It feels much more of a
just like a genuine informal conversation.
What is happening to podcasts?
And how do you see this trajectory?
Because it sounds like
you build this company
right at a beautiful time period
where all these Web conferences
are taking off
and this sharing of information
is happening in this medium now.
Absolutely.
It is definitely the future.
And we're really very well
positioned in all time.
from a launch perspective.
Podcasting is definitely
on an exponential growth curve
where brands are realizing
that a lot of their marketing spend
and tactics on things like events
are no longer applicable.
And so, they're looking for
additional tactics
to spend their money on.
And podcasting is definitely,
now we're at a million podcasts.
20% of them are active.
Actually 200 to 300,000 of those
were only added
in the last 60 days.
So, there's about 4,000 new shows
that are popping up every day.
So, the growth curve is huge.
And we have definitely seen
that as soon as we launched,
we had brands knocking on our door,
asking to be create podcast
and create shows.
And it's been really interesting
because oftentimes,
I get asked all the time like,
"Is it a saturated community?"
"Are there a lot of podcasts out there?"
And I always say,
"Well, let's compare it
to other forms of content.
There's six hundred plus million blogs.
There's 30 million YouTube channels.
There's 1.5 billion websites.
When we're looking at podcasting,
there's only one million podcasts.
And only 20% of those podcasts are active.
So, really, there's only 200,000
active podcasts.
So, I always say, brands
and indeed podcasters
who are in this space today
are definitely ahead of the hype curve.
And very similar to how
in the 1980's companies
had a phone number for their business
and then they had a website
and they had social media.
Similar to that.
I think that in the next five to 10 years,
every company and every person
will either have a podcast
or be advertising on one.
Fascinating. Okay, two questions
that I have to know the answer to that
are now jumping in.
First of all, why is it difficult
for brands to create podcasts?
And why does a brand like Gap
need to come to an agency and say,
"Hey, can you please help me
create this thing with high quality?"
That's the first question.
The second question is,
what are some tangible things
the average student like myself
that wants to start a podcast,
what are some critical things
that I need to take in mind,
whether it's the technology,
the reaching out to people,
the sharing of the content?
So, those two things I'm just
completely fascinated by right now.
Yeah, for sure.
So, I would say with brands,
it's definitely not that hard
to create a podcast.
I think any brand can do it.
But if you're looking
for a high production, high quality show
that matches the value of your brand,
then definitely you can't necessarily,
you have to have
a lot of different layers of a show.
So, you need someone
who's good at pre-production.
You need someone who's good at content.
The technical side,
which is the sound engineering,
the editing, the recording.
And there's the distribution.
Then there's the marketing.
So, there's just, and guess sourcing.
There's just so many different layers
to creating a really good show.
It's going to be very hard for you
to find that in one hire or two hire.
So, that is why I think oftentimes
if you're on a low budget
and you're an indie podcaster,
for sure you hire a freelancer
to help you.
But if you're a brand,
oftentimes you're looking
for high quality production.
You're going to need a team around you.
What are the costs
that are generally associated
with like an indie podcast?
So, let's say a friend of mine
wants to start a podcast,
thinking strategically,
what are the associated costs with that?
Well, so I would say for an indie podcast,
like if you are starting one right now
for university, the things to consider
is recording platforms.
I never recommend that people use Zoom.
Because Zoom is a conference line.
Not a podcast audio platform.
I know we're using it right now
and I'm totally turning a blind eye to it.
But for example,
a platform like Zencastr,
which is, I think it's free during covid,
otherwise it's $20 a month,
it is optimized for sound quality.
So, it is actually devised
for people who are podcasting.
And so, the sound quality is much higher.
So that is my first tip
as an indie podcaster.
Or if you're recording yourself
and you don't have budget to spend,
record on a platform
like Zencastr  or Cleanfeed.
Don't use platforms like Anchor,
your phone or Skype or Zoom.
Because the audio is usually
very low in it.
Like retention rate would be low.
I have to ask, though, because the way
that I was approaching
this program as well
as I'm seeing you, you're seeing me
the person is going to view this show,
especially on our Facebook page,
they're going to have the ability
to see us interact on video.
And it's almost like watching a TV show.
Now, this podcast that we're recording
is also going to be
on Spotify and Apple podcasts.
But I'm seeing the value of the video
that in 2020 is something
that is increasingly important.
Because while I imagine,
the audiobooks have been around
for a pretty long time,
and I've foresee podcast to run
for a long time, I know my friends and I,
we're looking for the video content
that we can see through our phone
and through our touch screens.
So, do you see that as being
an upcoming medium?
Or do you still think
that the audio part of it
is still the most crucial piece?
Yeah, so actually,
most of our clients, I would say,
would like a video component.
Because they have YouTube channels
that they upload their content on.
And so, typically what we do
is we record on Zencastr
and we have Zoom on mute
in the background.
So, you're still getting the video,
but your audio quality is much higher.
So, we actually do
a lot of video podcasts as well.
The other thing,
I'm readying this done for me
for the next episode.
The other thing I would also, so, yeah,
just use Zoom as your video component
and just use Zencastr as the audio.
The other thing I would say is,
Zencastr is coming out
with a video component
by the end of the summer.
I'm actually on the wait list for it.
So, it's going to be a watch all
in one component.
Because they recognize that people
do really want the video.
And I agree.
It's better engagement.
We're getting to know each other
in a very organic way.
And it's hard to bring that to life
as much as quickly
in an audio consumption format.
Okay. So, Fatima, I have to ask
because this is the second part
of the conversation
that I was very excited about.
This whole notion of raising capital.
How covid has impacted
the diversity of founders.
Whether it's the gender,
or whether it's of color or race.
Talk to me a little bit
about your insights
in regarding to this scene.
What has happened before covid
in terms of the entrepreneurship scene?
And then, how has this been accelerated
through covid?
So, two things on that.
I would say, for starters,
I think covid has had a very
uneven effect on women
because for the most part,
a lot of women are on the front line
in the service industries
right in the heart of the pandemic.
And secondly,
I think the brunt of unpaid work
falls on the majority of women.
Whether that's household chores,
taking care of your children,
taking care of the elderly,
which is in itself so difficult
when services are closed,
schools and daycares are shut.
So, I would say
if you're a female entrepreneur,
I can't even imagine raising
or running your company
and not only having
to reimagine your products and services
in the immediate short term and pivot
during this pandemic,
but also taking care of your children
full time, which in itself
is a full time job.
So, that would be my first thing.
I would say that the pre-existing barriers
that female founders face
before the pandemic
are further compounded with things
like access to finance,
access to mentors and networks
and gendered priorities.
The second thing I would say is,
in reality, there is no pipeline problem
when it comes to raising capital.
There are a ton of female founders.
And in fact, I was reading an article
by Business Insider and they said
that black female founders, specifically,
are the fastest growing population
of entrepreneurs.
So, investors that are claiming
that there are not enough
minority female founders to invest in
are clearly not looking hard enough.
And I think the clog in the pipeline
is basically resulting in founders
like myself or founders of color,
or just female founders in general,
not falling into the investors
preconceived notion of what
a successful entrepreneur constitutes up
and what they should look like
resulting in two things.
Either they become a part
of some diversity quota
and some minimal charity fund,
or we lose the opportunity to somebody
who looks more the part.
And so, myself included,
I was in the process of closing out
my seed round right before the pandemic,
right up to term sheets.
And because of the pandemic,
a lot of investors had to pull out
and actually ended up
being really good for us
because we quadrupled our revenue
and now don't need investment.
But we had to get really creative
in the short term
to bootstrap our services
so that we could stay afloat.
And I think a lot of founders
in my position who are women
are now looking at ways
to run their companies
without acquiring outside capital.
Wow. And is this different
than the founders that are male
and perhaps, that are not
in the minority race?
Is that specifically to the group
that you're referring to,
that you are seeing this behavior?
Yeah, I would definitely agree.
I mean, I would say that the stats
speak for themselves.
Like the average deal size
for men last year was 12 million.
And the average deal size
for women was five million.
If you look at the average deal size,
men have more than double.
But like the numbers aren't correlating
with the amount of female entrepreneurs
in the industry.
And that I understand. Right.
Like everyone has their personal
and conscious and unconscious biases.
You essentially want to invest in people
that look more like you.
And at the top level of investments,
it's mostly white males.
And so, I think part of the problem is
that investing companies, angels and VCs
need to start making sure
that their partners map that
of the general demographic.
And if they don't,
then they need to put in selection blinds
to remove their biases.
But, yeah, I mean, in the meantime,
I think definitely women are going to have
a really tough time bouncing back
from this experience
that we're going through.
Wow. Well, I'm definitely
going to remain optimistic in the end.
And hopefully, it's not as dire.
But it sounds incredible that you were
about to close the seed round
after the term sheets, covid hits,
and now you've quadrupled revenues.
And not just the fact that your valuation
is probably much higher than it was.
But now you're saying
that you're profitable
and you don't need to raise
the next investments.
Talk to me a little bit about this
National Speakers Bureau.
Why public speaking?
Why getting on stages
and sharing information, sharing stories?
Why do you do that?
I was approached by BNN Bloomberg
to start doing segments
and contribution columns
on topics that were
really extremely important to me.
And actually, diversity and inclusion
is one of the main topics
that I talk about.
Especially within the tech sector.
And so, I've just always been
really passionate about moving the dial.
Like moving to North America in itself
was moving the dial for me.
Because I grew up
in a very Middle Eastern culture,
which is very different
from what I've experienced here.
And so, I really wanted to share
not only my experience,
but how we can continue moving forward
from a diversity and inclusive efforts
and what companies need to be doing
to support entrepreneurs.
And so, I would say,
that's more my area of expertise,
along with tech and media trends for sure.
But I really enjoy public speaking.
I mean, obviously,
things have been put on a halt right now
with conferences and events being on hold.
But I've always really enjoyed
speaking to people.
Really sharing a lot of insights,
and it's more so 360s than feedback
has always been very mutual.
And I would say, public speaking
is definitely not for everyone.
But I just been one of the lucky.
I think I'm an extrovert.
So, it's worked really well for me.
But it's just one of those tactics
that I chose to build my personal brand.
And it worked really well for me.
First of all, I want to thank you again
for being so generous with your time.
It's been really inspiring to hear
both about your insights
about the tech ecosystem
and the financial side of it
and the raising capital,
but also in the podcasting side.
And I definitely took some notes
for myself on how to improve
for the next 200 episodes of the series.
But before we leave,
I have to put you on the spot one time
and ask you a personal question.
And I'd love to know three words
that you would use to describe yourself
or that any of your colleagues
would use to describe you
or anybody listening to you on stage,
how would they describe you.
Yeah. So, a good and bad, I want to try
to be as objective as possible.
I would say I am definitely,
I have a lot of hustle.
I think it's the DNA of all entrepreneurs.
We know it's 95% perspiration
and 5% inspiration.
So, definitely hustle
is something that I would say.
A little bit insane.
Crazy or insane would definitely be a word
that I would use to describe myself.
It's a combination of just like,
having a very crystallized dream
and focus in life
and just working tirelessly towards it.
And so, sometimes I think that
that can translate
into a type of intensity
that maybe doesn't resonate with everyone.
And I'm okay with that.
And I would say,
the third one is, oh, my goodness,
I'm like, it's so hard to narrow down
the third one.
I hate talking about myself in that way.
That's why it's the hardest question.
Yeah. It is a really hard question.
You've got me there.
You've stumped me.
I would probably say the last one
would be resilience.
Yeah. I would say that I'm just somebody
that like, because I don't know
if it's because I've been in sales
or where I've come from,
but just keep getting knocked down,
keep getting back up.
So, I don't take no for an answer.
Don't ask, don't get policy.
So, yeah, I would say hustle,
resilience and a little bit of crazy.
Which I think every needs.
One of the main things
that a lot of VCs on this show
have been telling me is that,
one of the skills
they consider most important
as you're starting
your entrepreneurial career,
is actually to boost sales.
And to understand what it's like
to get rejected ten times,
to only get one client.
And getting back up
and being able to deliver a message
clearly and concisely
so that it also impacts the other person
and not just yourself.
With this note, I need to send you off
to your next meeting [--]
But thank you very very much for the time.
This was fantastic.
And I'll definitely get back to you
on the new technologies
that I'm going to use.
I've already wrote them down for me.
Sounds good. Let me know.
Happy podcasting, Michael.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Take care.
Bye.