Marissa Orr, thank you for joining me
on 20 Minute Leaders.
How are you?
Thank you for having me.
I'm doing well today, thanks.
Looking forward to our chat.
I'm extremely excited for our chat
because I love the episodes
where I get to just hear people's journey.
And hear about
the different twists and turns they took
to their non-linear career pathways.
Yet it somehow ends up with
a very optimistic note
of passion and curiosity, which I think
is going to happen here as well.
So, Marissa, tell me a little bit about
your both experience
as a business executive in top companies
but also now as a business owner.
Yeah. So, I started working at Google
back in 2003 and that was before
the company had gone public.
I was working in New York City.
I graduated college
or grad school not too early,
not too long before then.
And actually got the Google interview
through this old Yahoo jobs board
called HotJobs at which
people your age wouldn't know about.
But anybody my age remembers it very well.
There was about 50 people
in the New York office of Google
at the time, now there's maybe 10,000.
So, it was a very different place.
I really got to grow up there in my career
because I worked there for 13 years
all through my early, mid,
late 20s and 30s.
And then, after 13 years
I left for a role at Facebook
and I was there
for about a year and a half.
And it was not the experience
that I had imagined when I joined.
And I go into detail about
only now in my book.
But essentially,
it was a pretty bad experience.
And everybody in my life
was telling me to go back to Google,
I had a great career there.
Or find another company in tech.
But that experience really put me
in a very deep, dark place
where I started asking myself
these big life questions like:
who am I;
and, what do I want.
And I knew there was something in me
that was never going to manifest
in the corporate world.
My potential is limited
as a very creative person.
Now, while I was at Google, I had started
this women's leadership series
that was a bit irreverent and counter
to the conventional wisdom,
and it started to grow in popularity.
I started doing lectures
at not only at Google
but other companies in New York City
and other colleges in New York City.
And at Facebook,
I really came to terms with the fact
that I wanted to devote my life
to that sort of thing,
speaking full time and writing a book,
turning my lecture series into a book.
So, I started doing that
while I was at Facebook.
And here I am now.
I don't want to paint the picture
because the context here is not just
that you are a successful executive
for over a decade at the top companies
in the tech scene in the world,
but when you decide
to make that transition
you're also a mother of three,
a single mother of three.
This is not just a random decision
that as a 24 year old, I can say,
yeah, of course, a lot of people
want to leave the corporate world
and start their own companies.
This is a little bit more complicated
than the average
24 year old mind set, right?
Absolutely.
It's a great point and call that to make
because it really defines
the essence of my journey.
Which is here I am,
I live in a nice neighborhood
in New Jersey,
I'm financially independent
and I have three kids to take care of,
a rent to pay,
and I'm not a financial risk taker.
So, the idea that I would leave this world
where I made this lucrative salary
at these great companies
and had a great career
and just bet it all on this pipe dream,
what it seemed like a pipe dream
because I'd never written anything before.
I mean, I had written but I had no name,
I had no social following,
I wasn't a recognized person,
I have never published anything.
The idea that I can get a book deal
or write a book and then become a speaker
and follow my passions
which is really absurd
from the outside in.
And even, I have to tell you,
in my own family,
and I'm very close to my parents
and they're wonderful and supportive.
But my mom is the daughter
of Eastern European immigrants
who really came here
and pull themselves up
from their boots.
It's very business oriented family.
Like the idea that I would do this
was so absurd.
And we didn't talk about the book
for about a year in my family.
It was it didn't exist.
Wow.
Yeah.
I knew how crazy it seemed.
And talking about it with them
upset me
because I really needed the support
and I know it upset them.
So, we just didn't talk about it.
And then I remember like one year
at Thanksgiving we're all drinking,
and then during dessert
my brother in law was like,
"So, how's the book going?"
And it was like the music stopped
and everyone's like, "Oh."
And so, I say that, because I think
it's really important to anyone
that is going on this journey.
I mean, you hear it
to the point where it's cliche,
but it's cliche because it's true.
Which is very very few people
understand what you're doing
and support it.
Because only you have the full picture
of what's going on.
Only you know
what you're truly capable of.
So, that was really difficult for me.
It was to depart from the standard story
of how my life was supposed to unfold.
The storyline that was approved
by my parents that I went along with
without thinking about,
and then the money piece
was probably even bigger than that.
So, I made a great salary
and I had a certain amount of savings.
And when I decided to do this,
I knew I was going to be
fired from Facebook.
I had this and I go into detail
about it in the book.
I got into this situation where I was,
it was just a bad situation.
So, knowing I was going to be fired
eventually,
that's when everyone was telling me,
like jump ship, go back to Google.
And that's when I made the decision,
"You know what?"
"I'm going to ride this out
as long as I can so I can get the salary
while I work on the book proposal."
So, one really important piece of this,
so, the summer of 2017,
I started writing the book proposal
in June of 2017.
And the very first thing I did
was I sat down
and I Googled how to write a book.
No joke.
Really?
Yeah. That was my first step.
I did all the research,
I have to write a proposal,
I bought a book
on how to write a book proposal.
And I would wake up,
keep in mind
I'm still working at Facebook,
so I'd wake up, I thought,
"When am I going to do this?"
I have three kids.
I have an hour and a half
commute each way.
So, I start waking up
at 4:30 in the morning.
And I worked on the book proposal
for about an hour and a half.
And then I would get the kids up
and I would get to work
and they would go to school.
And any free time that I had,
I was like possessed with this idea.
I didn't tell very many people about it.
Which is very different
than how I'd handled
creative ideas in the past.
I get all excited, I tell everyone.
And then [--].
I decided this was going to be different
in order to take myself seriously.
And to really do this
I couldn't tell people about it.
I needed to prove to myself
that I was taking myself seriously.
So, I did end up getting fired,
again, I write all about it in the book,
in September of 2017.
I was about 95% done
with the book proposal.
And I think that's the key.
Because I probably
would have gone back to Google
or a different company,
If you didn't have the momentum
for the book, right?
Exactly.
Now, just for the context for listeners,
when you say book proposal,
is this like an initial draft of the book?
Or is this an abstract for the book?
Yeah. So, it's what you have to write
in order to get a book deal.
And a lot of people,
and especially, I think this is a point
to just pause on
for people that are younger
that don't have the context.
A lot of people self publish today.
But that's where
being a single mom comes in.
I knew that nobody makes money
on books these days.
So, I knew that the way
I was going to make money was speaking,
which is my passion anyway.
And in order to get the fees
as a speaker that I needed,
I needed to have a book published
by a traditional publisher.
Because if I went the grassroots scrapie
like gain a social media following,
gain power that way
and then self publish or whatever,
it was going to take too long.
I didn't have the luxury to do that
and I was starting from zero.
But I knew that
I really believed in my book idea
and I knew it was going to be
a great book.
So, the book proposal
is what you have to write
in order to get a book deal
with the publisher.
You don't have to write one
if you're self publishing.
And there's good reasons to self publish.
And there's reasons to go
with the traditional publisher.
So, I started with the traditional
and the book proposal took me many months.
I mean, I really put my blood,
sweat and tears into it.
And once I was done,
that's when I started looking for agents.
And at this point,
so I was fired in September,
now it's like being in November
and I have no contacts in book publishing.
I don't know anyone.
So, I just started reaching out
to everybody in my network
asking if they could help me
by introducing me
to anyone they know
that has anything to do with books.
They wrote a book,
they know someone who wrote a book,
they know someone who works in publishing.
They read books.
Right. They read books.
I was meeting with a million people
and trying to figure out
how to get an agent.
Because it's really hard
just to get an agent.
Forget about getting a deal.
So, I end up getting an agent.
We send the proposal out
to 20 publishing houses.
18 of them wrote back and said,
"We love the idea."
"It's provocative, we love the voice."
But, to summarize,
this isn't exactly what they said,
but this is the sentiment,
"It's too risky."
Because the way business books work,
they give deals to people they know
who have a following.
So that when the book comes out,
the publisher doesn't have
to spend money marketing it.
This is how business books work.
And this is why in order to get published
as a business book,
you need to be an academic
or a researcher.
You need to be like an Adam Grant
or Simon Sinek or Brené Brown,
because then it's not risky.
But I represented a huge risk
because who's going to buy
a business book
from somebody without credentials
and without the academic or the title.
So, 18 out of 20 loved it,
but I was too risky.
One we never heard back from.
And then the one
at HarperCollins Leadership,
which was a developing entity
within the bigger umbrella, loved it.
And against all odds, got the deal.
Then I had to write the book.
I didn't even address your question
which is what is the proposal.
So, the proposal is really
you selling the book.
And now, if you're Justin Timberlake,
you don't have to write a proposal.
Like they write one for you, basically
and say, "Can you sign with us?"
But if you're not,
you need to explain the book, the concept,
what it's about, and you have to sell it.
Which is a very different thing
than just writing the book.
It's like sending a slide deck
to an investor.
Yes.
But it also has a very detailed outline
of each chapter.
It has like two or three sample chapters.
It has a market analysis
so you have to do all the work for it.
Oh, yeah.
I had a whole customer segmentation.
And I had done a lot
of stuff like that at Google,
a little at Facebook, where I knew
how to sell something.
I knew how to sell a value proposition,
I knew how to market something.
So, I wrote that proposal
like my life depended on it
and that's what a proposal is, so.
Wow. Okay, so talk to me a little bit
about Lean Out,
and then I'd love to also hear
about the different speaking engagements
and the some of the messages
that you're bringing to the world now
through your journey.
So what is Lean Out about?
I'm guessing that it has something to do
with something that Sheryl wrote.
But please tell me.
So Sheryl Sandberg, of course,
she's the CEO of Facebook
and she's the author of Lean In.
And if you're a woman my age,
you've probably read Lean In
because this came out in 2013
and it was like a bombshell
like women and leader.
This really defined modern feminism
for the women of my generation.
And my book is really a counter argument
because the premise of Lean In really
is that women are oppressed
by stereotypes and bias, and that's why
there's so few female executives
in the corporate world
and all that kind of stuff.
And gender bias,
all the popular themes of today.
My book really is the counter argument
which essentially,
it's funny I haven't done an interview
on the book in a while, so I'm like,
"What was my messaging?"
So, essentially what Lean Out is about
is that it's really has nothing to do
with women, it has to do
with the system set up
in the corporate world.
Which are basically these were,
these are corporate hierarchy
for power and dominance.
It's a zero sum game
And it was designed by the titans
of the Industrial Age.
And so, for example,
there's research that shows
that compared to men, women,
so compared to women, men prefer
competitive zero sum work environments
and they perform better in men.
Whereas women prefer
and performed better
in collaborative win-win
work environments.
And by its nature, as a triangle,
the corporate world is a zero sum game,
and that's number one.
Number two is that compared to men,
women have more life goals
and they're of greater variety.
Whereas men have fewer
and they're more focused
on money and rank and their career.
And so what happens is with promotions,
when you get escalating
management responsibility,
that usually pre-covid,
required you to be in the office
or FaceTime.
And that compromises
the balance and flexibility
that women really desire
to reach a greater variety of polls.
Now, there are no value judgments.
One is not better than the other.
But we have to take a look
at the system at work
and why it is biased
towards certain traits.
Because what really is happening
is that the people that make it to the top
make it because they have a certain
cocktail of personality traits
that lend themselves
to a zero sum game
for power and dominance.
A lot of women don't aspire
to manage large teams.
That was an issue with me.
And that's the only way to get promoted.
And it's seen as a lack of ambition.
I mean, that couldn't be further
from the truth.
Like you can make an impact
and have ambition
without managing large teams.
In fact, I felt like being a manager
diminished my impact.
Because I'm super creative,
I was doing a lot of story development
and training, and I think
that puts a limit on the ceiling
for people who don't aspire
toward escalating amounts
of power and authority.
So, it's all about that.
But it's told through stories
about my time at Google and Facebook.
So, I say that because it's not
some dry academic analysis of work,
it's actually quite funny.
And I wrote it for two reasons.
One, I always felt
like there was something wrong with me.
Like I didn't fit in right,
like a square peg in a round
hole in the corporate world.
And I thought that was a reflection
of something was wrong with me.
And over 15 years,
I started to understand things
from a new perspective,
that there was nothing wrong with me.
And I wrote the book I needed to read
when I was starting out my career.
It is a very honest assessment
of what that world is all about
and what it requires to succeed.
Whereas I didn't know
what game I was playing
when I started out,
I just didn't understand it.
And so, my book is really,
here's the game you're playing
and if you love that, go for it.
If you don't, nothing's wrong with you.
It doesn't mean you don't have ambition.
And it's just the nature of the game.
You can change the rules,
but you can also change how you play it.
So, it's all about that.
And then I also wrote it,
I didn't hear any voices
in the public conversation
of women at work that I could relate to
or that I identify with,
so I wrote it for other women
to feel heard and understood.
And I think that's
what it's really accomplished.
I get messages
from women all over the world
thanking me
for putting their thoughts and feelings
into words that they didn't really know
how to express.
So, that's the book.
There's one other thing I wanted to say.
What about the responses
from the other gender?
I'm guessing that quite a few people
from your past have read the book,
took interest in it.
I'm guessing that it's not just to women
that read it.
Because it does sound
like you're painting a picture here that,
maybe controversial is not the right word,
but it does seem that
it is provocative.
So, how was the reception of that?
So, the reception
about it being provocative,
everybody leading up to is like,
"Oh, you're going to get
tons of hate, man."
"It's really divisive."
But I think for anyone who reads it,
it's not.
It's common sense
because it's a perspective
that they hadn't thought about,
but when it's shared,
it makes so much sense.
And I always say,
I never really understood why
it would be provocative.
Because if Sheryl Sandberg and I
both have a goal of helping women
and we both have
two different perspectives
on how to do that,
it shouldn't be controversial.
The women's voices shouldn't be limited
to one woman
who dominates the conversation,
and anyone who disagrees
has to be anti-woman.
It's really counter to an antithetical,
to the course of human progress.
To be able to say
just this one perspective
means that you support women.
And I think that it does
a lot of damage to women.
So, the reception has only been really
like women reaching out from,
I can tell you,
it's like they write me love letters
and I love it.
Because I clearly gave them a voice
and that's what I wanted to do.
The second half of the book, I think,
would be really interesting to men.
And the men that have read it
really appreciate it.
Because at the end of the day
it's not even about men and women.
It's about a certain type of person
that does well in that world.
And both men and women,
they do and they don't.
Maybe a little more women than men.
But there's like a whole universe
of men out there that can relate
to a lot of the things.
I did a Reddit AMA last year.
That's when I really reached more men.
But I think men assume
that they're not going to relate
because it's a female book.
But then if they do read it,
they end up really relating to it.
Sure. That's amazing.
So, 20 minutes go by so fast.
It's unbelievable.
If there is one message
that I can take away from this
or a lot of my friends,
whether they're guys or girls
at Stanford, for example,
could take away from either the book
or your different speaking engagements
or your journey as a whole,
what would the message be?
Well, the message of the book
at its very core is to,
it's again, cliche,
but it's to be who you are and own it.
And a lot of that
is about defining success
on your own terms.
Because there are so many things
we can get caught up,
and even school,
where success is defined for you
and people just go along with the script.
So, getting promoted at work,
that's like the definition of success.
But if you don't want certain things
that the system doles out as rewards,
you need to take a step back
and really take a hard look
at who you are, what you want.
And then let go of the noise around you.
And I really had to do that
on this journey to be an entrepreneur.
It's tough.
I'll close with this
because I know a lot of people,
this is a really the topic
that you talk about a lot.
I was in the corporate world for 15 years.
I made a great salary.
I had the prestige of working
at Google and Facebook
and all these amazing experiences
and security and benefits.
But there was something in me
that felt empty.
And now that I'm on this opposite journey,
it's very rewarding
but it's also very difficult.
So the point I'm making is
each has its trade offs
and you have to really
recognize that going in.
The one way I heard it put
that captures it beautifully
is when you leave the corporate world
to start your own thing,
you trade depression for anxiety.
And I think that's the best,
most concise way to put it.
It is not easy.
I mean, I miss that world
for so many reasons,
I would never trade
what I'm doing now for anything.
At the same time,
it's tough but that's life.
And I'd rather live doing this
and taking risks
and seeing how far I can go.
So, that's just me.
But I want an end on that note.
Marissa, thank you very very much.
This is wonderful.
I have to ask the last question,
three words that you would use
to describe yourself.
I would say
creative, free spirited and resilient.
Marissa, thank you very much.
It sounds like an incredible journey,
a difficult and joyous and optimistic
and rewarding at the end.
And definitely thank you
for spreading this message at the end.
I think, looking at the world
that I'm growing up in,
it is sometimes cut throat
and there's a lot
of competition sometimes.
I'm very fortunate
to be in a community where I feel
that there's a lot of collaboration,
even more than there was competition.
But at the end, it's about
finding your personal passion and reward.
And so thank you for sharing that message.
And stay safe and stay healthy.
Thank you.
Thanks for having me.
And we forgot to mention
that you also started a podcast in March.
I know we're out of time
but just give me two sentences on that.
I'll quickly say to follow me
on Instagram, LinkedIn, Twitter,
Marissa Beth Orr.
B-E-T-H is my middle name.
And then I just started
a podcast in March called,
Nice Girls Don't Watch The Bachelor.
And that's meant to be irreverent.
It's a story
I can go into it another time.
But it's available on iTunes
and Google Play
and Everywhere Podcasts are.
So, thank you.
Wonderful.
Thank you very much.
Stay safe and stay healthy.
Thank you.